Guide to the Charles Ives (1815-1880) Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Ives papers
1838-1897
MS 932
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Correspondence, poems, orations and other writings, and miscellaneous legal papers that relate to Charles Ives and his immediate family. Some of his poems appear in Chips from the Workshop (1843). The orations and addresses concern political activities and also include notes and fragments of Isles of Summer, (1880).
Ives, Charles, 1815-1880
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the Collector's Shop, 1945.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Ives papers consist of correspondence, poems, orations and other writings, and miscellaneous legal and financial papers relating to Ives and his immediate family.
Personal and professional letters to Ives comprise the greater part of the correspondence; pages from Ives' letter copybook comprise the rest.
Some of the poems are manuscript versions of those appearing in his Chips from the Workshop (1843). A number were written during his periods of poor health and reflect that condition. The orations and addresses concern Ives' local political activities and affiliations. Notes (some in shorthand) and fragments from his Isles of Summer (1880) are included among the writings.
The legal and financial papers relate mainly to Ives' law practice and to his estate. A section of miscellaneous items—newspaper clippings, unidentified writings and papers to Charles Ives, Jr. (d. 1883)—follows the legal and financial papers.
The correspondence is arranged chronologically with Ives' copybook following the letters to him. The rest of the papers are arranged by type and then chronologically.
The Charles Ives papers were purchased from the Collector's Shop in 1945.
Biographical / Historical
Lawyer; born in New Haven, CT; graduated from the Lancastrian School in 1831 and began work in a printing office; entered Yale Law School and graduated in 1846; he was admitted to the bar that year and opened a law office in New Haven; elected to the Conn. General Assembly from New Haven in 1853; represented East Haven in 1865, 1867, and 1868; Speaker of the House in his last two years of office.
Law; Literature -- History and criticism; Connecticut -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; New Haven (Conn.); Poetry; Lawyers; Legislators; Poets; Ives, Charles, 1815-1880
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1838-1848 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1854-1856 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1857-1868 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1869-1879 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1880-1883 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1892-1897 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letterbook, 1870-1878 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Poems, 1834-1853 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chips from the Workshop [partial manuscript], [1843?] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Orations, 1841, 1844, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters to the editor, 1842, 1870, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Isles of the Summer [notes and printed pages], [ca. 1880] (Box 1, Folder 19 - 20)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 21 - 22)
  - Notebooks in shorthand, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Notes in shorthand, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Legislative notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Test cases from legal studies, [1846?] (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Leases and deeds, 1855-1891 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous licenses and certificates, 1846-1879 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers, 1874-1897 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Copy of Ives' will, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Papers re: Ives' estate, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Financial record, 1853-1857 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Receipts, 1837-1878 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Penmanship notebook, 1835 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Miscellaneous writings [by Ives?], 1838, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Invitations and business cards, 1868-1875, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter, 1851-1881 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Charles Ives, Jr.
    - Note to his aunt, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Document of admission to the bar, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Memorial resolution, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letter to the editor, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1833-1864, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Clippings re: persons named Ives, 1889-1895, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)